Preliminary Inventory of the Thomas James Orbison papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Thomas James Orbison papers
1919-1922
XX107
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 slide box, 1 oversize folder (3.3 linear feet)
Diaries, writings, photographs, and memorabilia relating to relief work in Latvia at the end of World War I. Diaries and typescript also available on microfilm (3 reels).
Orbison, Thomas J. (Thomas James), 1866-1938.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Portions also available on microfilm: diary and "The Bermondt Affair" typescript (3 microfilm reels)
Biographical Note
Chief, Latvian Mission, American Relief Administration European Children's Fund, 1919-1920.
Scope and Content of Collection
Diaries, writings, photographs, and memorabilia relating to relief work in Latvia at the end of World War I.
American Relief Administration. European Children's Fund.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Latvia.; Slides (Photography)
- Typewritten copy of diary written by Dr. Orbison while serving with the American Relief Administration in Latvia, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Manuscript copy of diary (Box-folder 1: 2)
- "The Bermondt Affair," typescript copy of article by Dr. Orbison (Box-folder 1: 3)
- "Review of Latvia and the Activity of the Latvian Children's Relief Association," typescript, 1921 February - 1922 June (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Children's letters and hand-painted pictures presented to Dr. Orbison by the "American Children Kitchen at No. 4 Dunamunde Str., Hagensberg" (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Felt-covered folder, with hand-painted and embroidered design on front cover, containing photographs and scroll thanking Dr. Orbison for the assistance rendered to the "poor Russian military families" in Riga, 1920 July 20 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Letter of gratitude to Dr. Orbison from Ulmanis, Prime Minister of Latvia, 1920 July 23 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Album of photographs with metal plate on cover inscribed to Dr. Orbison by people of Dvinsk (Donaburg, Latvia), 1920 July 23 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Gray leather album of photographs presented "by the Strand Section composed of very poor fishing communities (near Riga),", 1920 July 11 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Red buckram folio containing photographs, letters, and other mementos expressing thanks and gratitude from the people of Latvia (Box-folder 2: 3)
- "Children, Inc.," manuscript regarding Orbison's relief work in Latvia (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Oversize materials (Box 4)
  - Large album of photographs, hand-woven design and heavy metal plaque on front cover, presented to Dr. Orbison by the city of Courland (Latvia), where the first American Relief Administration feeding station was opened
  - Suede case with metal plaque, corners, and clasp, containing scroll of thanks and photographs, presented to Dr. Orbison by the people of Riga, 1920 July 24
  - Leather case with multi-colored, enameled metal corners and plaque on front cover, containing scroll expressing appreciation to Dr. Orbison from members of the dental profession of the Free Clinic for Children, Riga, Latvia
- Slides (Slide cabinet)
  Scope and Contents note
  5 slides depicting the covers of the albums in the collection.
- Incremental materials (Box 5, oversize folder)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.